Oh, my system is trying to do three
things at once. So, give it just a
moment.
And it's now starting to admit everyone.
There we go. Okay.
Hello and good afternoon everyone. Uh
this is Dominic Earllo with the
Department of Health and uh we're here
to administratively or the department is
here to administratively support these
committee hearings and meetings. This is
the propagation committee. Um and so
welcome to it. Um just a couple of
housekeeping items for people. Um and
we'll be putting some of this
information in the chat as the meeting
continues. Um but while people are
joining into the meeting, we figure we
always go through this to give people
that moment or two to get into the
meeting and orient it a little bit. So
basically the um the information being
shown on screen right now is the email
for the medical psilocybin program, the
program website and the advisory board
website and I will also be putting that
into the chat here in just a moment. Um
in addition to that uh the chair of this
committee is uh Chris Pescuski and uh so
Chris will be uh running this meeting
but we are here from the department of
health side to help support him in this
process and it looks like the uh
individuals joining in has slowed down a
little bit Chris so I'll turn it on over
to you and you can go on ahead and
start.
>> Thank you Dominic.
Um, yeah, I'm Chris Biscus, but I'd like
to start out today's meeting. If we
could just take maybe 30 seconds to uh
have a little bit of silence just to
acknowledge all the the suffering going
on in our community, all the suffering
going on in our state and throughout our
country and throughout the world right
now. Um, it's a big part of reason why
I'm here and I just think it's important
for us to um just sit in that for a
minute. So, if you please bear with me,
I'll set a timer
Man,
All right. Thank you for uh allowing me
that 30 seconds. And um for those of you
who don't know me, I'm I'm looking
through the list of attendees here. Um
and I think I've met or talked with most
of you before, but um for those of you
who don't know me, I'm a Marine Corps
veteran. And for a long time, I was
really struggling with um just
uh my transition back from the military
life. And you know, I was had a pretty
bad alcohol problem before I even joined
the Marine Corps. And I I kind of got
supercharged there. I deployed a couple
times to Iraq and Afghanistan. and um
you know saw a fair bit of action and I
was um wounded by a car bomb at one
point and so it I dealt with some
traumatic brain injury, PTSD along with
substance use and um and a lot of
depression after I got out. So pretty
much all of the qualifying conditions
for um the medical psilocybin act I was
dealing with at one point in time and
you know psychedelics have really helped
me come back from that and so this is
that's how I got involved in all this
and I've been developing a a good
relationship with medicine for the last
three and a half years and
um I'm working um to become a licensed
facilitator with in a program in
Colorado
uh so I can help with the upcoming UNM
study for veterans and first responders
using the whole mushroom and I'm really
excited about that and I'm excited to be
a part of all of this and work with you
all uh on this legislation. Um so
um I've created a short agenda
Um,
is there anybody
did you have any other updates you
wanted to give, Dominic?
>> Uh, no, Chris. And I did put the agenda
in the chat so that people can see that.
>> Excellent.
>> Uh, and here I'll also I do have it on
the slide. So, let me
sorry the uh it is running slightly
slow. There we go.
And do we have any
legislators that like is um Senator
Steinborn in here? Does he want to speak
or any other legislators?
I don't see anybody that I recognize.
>> Okay.
>> I don't don't see them here, Chris.
>> Excellent.
>> Jeff Senator Jeff Steinborn often logs
in just as Jeff, but I don't see him
here for right now. He sometimes uh does
join in a little later with legislature
starting here in just a little more than
a week. I know his schedule's been
pretty busy. So uh but he's been trying
to attend as many meetings as he can.
>> Yeah. Um excellent. Well, then we can go
into introductions for the rest of the
committee meeting members. Um, if you
want to be an active participant in
this, I I would appreciate if you
introduce yourself and let me know any
affiliations that you have and whether
you're in state or out of state, please.
And I think the slide is displaying how
to raise your hand and then uh I believe
Ishma or Ishmael will uh will turn on
your mic if you raise your hand and
introduce yourself, please. Fantastic.
Thank you for that, Chris. And yes,
anyone who wishes to participate, please
do raise your hand and I will
sequentially begin to unmute so you can
uh introduce yourselves.
>> Can I uh
>> Dominic,
>> did I catch you in that in the other
um
meeting that we we can't have video on
this? I would really like to see
people's faces if possible, but if
that's going to cause a problem.
>> Yeah. So, there there's two reasons for
it. One is uh just bandwidth. We found
that uh and this is not just in teams,
it's on other platforms as well that
when we have quite a few people on
people who are in rural areas end up um
because of the bandwidth they end up
dropping out fairly regularly and so
missing large chunks of the meeting
simply due to our internet um status
around the state. Um and so we want to
make sure people can at least
participate. Um and then the other
aspect is uh and this one may sound a
little funny but a lot of you may
remember it from during COVID when lots
and lots of meetings were happening
virtually where people would see things
in backgrounds that were not necessarily
appropriate. And so since these also are
public recordings, we just want to make
sure that we are not um creating items
that are potentially problematic and
have to not share videos because there's
something inappropriate in the
background. So, um, that that's
basically the main reason. So,
>> fantastic. Well, without further ado,
let's get the show on the road. Uh,
Crystal Romero, I have unmuted yourself.
You may now have to unmute yourself on
the top right corner there as you can
follow the instructions on the screen.
Um, yeah, begin when ready.
>> Hi everyone and hello Dominic and hello
uh Chris. Uh, my name is Crystal Romero.
I am uh also a veteran and uh battle
buddy to Chris Piscus. Uh he and I uh
worked together on this uh legislation
as well as
uh will be working at the UNM program
together. I'm really happy to be here
and proud to be here and I look forward
to uh to the good things that we can
bring to the state of New Mexico. Thank
you so much for having me.
>> Thank you for that. Next we have Matthew
Armstrong. Matthew, I have enabled your
mic. If you can please unmute yourself
and introduce yourself when ready.
>> Uh yes, sir. My name is Matthew
Armstrong. I'm currently in New Mexico.
I'm a Jiuway descendant and I'm here
just to watch how this unfolds. Really,
I'm I believe in ancient medicines. I
believe that there are communities that
need a lot of healing. So, I'm I'm here,
man.
>> Fantastic. Thank you very much for that.
Next, we have Kate Hawk. Kate, I have
unmuted yourself. Uh you have to
manually now unmute and begin when
ready.
>> Hi, everybody. I'm Kate Hawk. I'm up in
Santa Fe and I'm attending as many of
these interrelated meetings um as
possible. I've been involved as a trauma
therapist for 40 years. I've done
everything from Native American trauma
project director to Bernie man harm
reduction. done the maps MDMMA training,
the Colorado natural medicine
facilitator training and uh most
recently I've just in in South Africa
with Ebogga ceremonies. I've had been
hospitalized maybe four times with
concussions that knocked me out for a
few hours. So, uh, brain care is of
interest, but also especially trauma and
just making these, uh, services
available through our our state. So,
thank you very much.
>> Thank you very much for that. Next, we
have Brenda. Brenda, I've enabled your
mic. When you're ready to speak, please.
>> Hello. Hi, Chris. It's good to see you
and be on the board. Um, well, hello. My
name is Brenda Bergard and I'm on the
medical psilocybin advisory board, chair
of the education and training and I'm a
therapist trained with MAPS and I'm the
president of decriminalization of
psychedelics of New Mexico and I've had
various experiences with psychedelics
and um uh thank you Chris for having um
us all here today in this meeting.
>> Thank you very much for that. Next we
have Brett Phelps. Brett, I have enabled
your mic. When you're ready, please
begin.
>> Hey, good afternoon everybody. Um Chris,
thanks for yeah running this committee
and Dominic all the department of health
guys. Yeah, good to see you all. Um my
name is Brett Phelps. I'm an attorney in
uh based out of Las Vegas, New Mexico. I
live in Mora. Um really yeah, just happy
to happy to help get this program off
and running any way that that I can.
I've been involved in um cannabis policy
and and that kind of work. So love to
see what you know what New Mexico's
doing. Um yeah, really excited for all
the people on the on the board and all
the DO people, you know, making this the
the best program we can. So happy to be
here and yeah, use my legal skills to uh
help us out any way I can. So thanks for
having me.
Thank you. Next we have Desba. Desba, I
have allowed your mic. When ready,
please begin.
>> A this is Desba. I'm also um on the
medical advisory board, a medical
psilocybin advisory board. I'm chairing
the um equity access and cultural
considerations committee. Um I am from
Northern New Mexico and based in Santa
Fe. I'm a massage therapist, licensed
massage therapist, but also um a part of
the film industry. So, thank you, Chris,
for um doing this.
>> Fantastic. Thank you so much for that.
And just before I go on to the next
participant, we have a message in the
chat there by Eric Bucker who just says,
"Hello everyone." So, thank you for
that. Uh next, we have uh Mitchell.
Mitchell, I have enabled your mic.
Whenever you're ready, please begin.
>> Hello everyone. Uh, my name is Mitchell
Tapen. Um, and I'm a psychedelic
enthusiast, friend of Chris, and um,
just looking to support this program and
help it thrive.
>> Thank you very much for that. Next, we
have John.
John, when you are ready, I have enabled
your mic. Please begin when you're
ready.
Hi, my name is John. Uh, I'm here in
Albuquerque. Uh, I grew up here in New
Mexico. Um, [snorts]
um, I'm just a local home micologist and
I've done some work with some of the
local gourmet farms and I just want to
see how I can be of assistance in this
and get the medicine to everyone.
>> Thank you very much for that. Next, we
have Tori. Tori, I have enabled your
mic. When you're ready, please begin.
>> Tori, I believe your mic is still on
mute. Um, just to inform you to unmute,
you have to go on the top right.
>> There we have it. Fantastic.
>> There we go. Hello everyone. My name is
Tori Armrest. My company is Satori Farms
and I was the first to receive a license
in Oregon under Measure 109 to legally
grow psilocybin. And I am really excited
for New Mexico and want to be a resource
um to y'all and we have we've gone
through a lot of trials and tribulations
and um I think New Mexico is going to
going to have a great program and I want
to help in whatever way possible. Thanks
for having me.
>> Thank you for that. Next we have Manuel.
Manuel, I have enabled your mic. Please,
when you are ready, you may begin.
>> Uh hello everyone. Uh my name is Manuel
Grigo. I'm uh native to Albuquerque and
uh I just wanted to say I appreciate the
work the committee is doing around
psilocybin New Mexico and I'm grateful
I'm just grateful to be a part of the
dialogue and look forward to
contributing u in any way I can.
Thank you very much for that. Next we
have David. David, I have enabled your
mic. When you are ready, please begin.
Hello everybody. My name is David
Austiniac. I currently operate the Art
Farm unincorporated.
Uh that's a gourmet mushroom farm out of
Sandia Park, New Mexico. So I currently
reside in Sandia Park, New Mexico.
um a highly supportive psychedelic
advocate and so I've had experience
cultivating mushrooms for over a decade.
So I'm just here to see how things go
and give any advice I can.
>> Thank you very much for that. Next we
have Estan. Estan, when you are ready, I
have enabled your mic. You may begin
when ready.
>> Good afternoon everybody. Uh my name is
Stevon Hernandez. I am the owner of New
Mexico Fungi based out of here in
Albuquerque. Um I am also the president
of the New Mexico Micology Guild where
we advocate and support for local
mushroom farmers in New Mexico. Uh
really we are looking to ensure that all
New Mexican mushroom farmers are given
an equal opportunity to actually
participate in this program and prevent
out of state interests from overrunning
our local economy.
>> Thank you very much for that. Next we
have Zack. Zach, I have enabled your
microphone. When you're ready, you may
begin.
Just as a reminder to unmute yourself,
there is a microphone icon on the top
right. Make sure to click that to unmute
yourself. Zach, in this context, I have
uh enabled your mic, but you have to
manually unmute. So, just let us know
when when you're ready.
If you're facing any issues, drop a
message into the chat and we can
probably get back to you if you're
having any issues there.
Okay, what we will do is we'll move on
to Evan uh Evan, sorry. And uh if uh we
get a chance, maybe you can raise your
hand again when uh if your microphone is
working. Often it may be the case that
if you're experiencing any trouble,
maybe dropping out of the call and then
joining back in may resolve that. So
just a little hint and tip. Um, Evan, oh
Evan, sorry, my apologies. Uh, I have
allowed your mic. When you're ready,
please begin.
>> Hey, uh, Ishmail, it is a pleasure to
hear your voice. You are the most
calming feature in the room. I really
appreciate your patience with everybody.
My name is Gregory Evans. I'm here as a
contributor
um, in whatever capacity I'm able. Uh I
have a [clears throat] detailed uh
interest in cultivation
um cultivation systems. I'm currently
you know like I grow things at home. I
love the idea of industrializing things
and making research possible. There are
a few topics that I want to like kind of
like keep track of while I'm here. Um,
one of those is to ensure that we do not
impact the ability for people to
cultivate at home. Uh, I want to monitor
the development of compliance software
and also include inside that research
capacity for cultivation techniques and
output. So figuring out what types of
methods and what environments produce
consistent or variable results in our
final product and you know connect all
of that to analytics and testing which
is kind of a different committee but I
I'm here as offering to bridge some of
those conversations. Um I am very
interested in genetics tracking,
breeding and traceability um and
[clears throat] breeding verification
systems. I want to promote licensing for
lab production as opposed to retail
distribution and I also want licensing
for genetic storage and distribution and
genetics verification. Uh I think that's
all.
Um there are some incredible people in
the room today. It's an honor to be
here.
>> Thank you very much for that. Next, we
have Tay Davis. Tay, I have enabled your
mic. Please begin when ready.
Hello, my name is Taye Davis and I am a
uh psilocybin advocate and uh just
someone who has personal use with micro
doing and I understand the benefits and
just curious and interested in how this
will unfold and come about. Willing to
assist in any capacity. Thank you.
Thank you for that. Finally, we have
Maxmillian.
I have enabled your mic. Please begin
when ready.
>> Hi everyone. I'm Maximillian Esparza. Um
I'm currently based in El Paso but
relocating to Silver City, New Mexico.
I'm a mushroom farmer. I uh run El Paso
mushroom and we provide fresh mushrooms
and mushroom supplements to the
community. And I'm also co-founder of
Mycelia Matters uh which is an
organization that hosts large scale
events in Texas, New Mexico, California.
And we uh bring education and advocacy
to all things fungi and mushrooms. I'm
really excited uh for New Mexico paving
a path forward for affordable and
equitable access to and I would love to
uh support and contribute.
>> Fantastic. Thank you very much everyone
who has shared. Um I open the floor now
back to the chair. When ready please
take the floor.
>> All right. Thank you everybody for
introducing yourselves. Um can one of
you bring up the bylaws that we were
going to review?
>> I'll have those up in just a moment.
We're going to skip the review agenda
because that's in the chat. If everybody
would like to take a look at what we're
going to talk about
a good turnout, 40 people. Thank you all
for coming.
Incredible.
Okay. And just to check, can you see the
screen there with the bylaws? Okay,
great. And I'm just increasing it a
little bit so you should see it a little
bit easier in a moment.
>> All right, go on ahead, Chris.
>> Thank you, Tony. Um, okay. So, I just
wanted to put out some bylaws so we can
kind of all have general rules of how
we're going to work together on this.
Um, article one, obviously the committee
known as the committee. Two, this is I
was appointed by the board to to run
this committee. Um and everything that
we're doing here is just a advi you know
compat um advisory capacity and so
anything we come up with has to be voted
on by the board. Um
and the purpose is to develop
evidenceinformed safety focused and
affordable affordabilityly conscious
recommendations related to the
cultivation production processing
testing quality assurance of psilocybin
in New Mexico's medical psilocybin
program committee's work is intended to
support patient safety product quality
and consistency and reasonable costs for
qualified patients and program
participants.
Oh, it's a mouthful. Sorry.
Um, article four I copied straight out
of the board approved committee uh
proceedings. It's very vague, I feel
like. So, I kind of expanded that scope
of responsibilities and put it in a uh
another document that I think can go
over in a little while.
um because I don't think this really
encaps you know uh brings out everything
that we have to do and um
yeah I I guess we'll go into that a
little more detailed later.
Um can everybody see these or does does
somebody want me to continue reading
these sections? I I don't mind.
You want me to continue reading them?
You can raise your hand. If not, we'll
just carry on.
Um okay let's go down to article five.
Um so for the members it anybody who
comes and is participating in the
meetings uh are members and hopefully we
have a good mix of people from various
expertise ranges that'll help us put
this all together. Um I think this is a
New Mexico program. I want it to be, you
know, for New Mexicans and by New
Mexicans. So, anything that we end up
voting on, I would like to keep uh
limited to New Mexicans voting on it.
And so, uh anybody from out of state
won't count to have towards the quorum
or have voting rights. Um if you're
disruptive during meetings, you might be
removed if we have to. And I I think
everybody has been amazing in all of
these meetings so far. So hopefully
that'll continue.
Um as we covered earlier, I was
appointed by the board and these are my
responsibilities and uh we got we got a
lot of ground to cover in the next uh
year to get this out. So, um, yeah,
hopefully we can
just keep this moving. Um, I'll be
calling meetings as frequently as as I
think we need to. My initial
uh
kind of thought is that we'll probably
need to be doing these about every two
weeks. Although um is it is it going to
be a burden on your team Dominic to do
these during the legislative session?
>> We are here to help and uh to serve. The
only thing that may happen during
legislative session is some individuals
what we internally will make sure that
you have uh support. But for example, I
may not be able to attend some of the
meetings, but I will watch the videos
and catch up if that happens. and the
same with some of our other staff uh
depending on our legislative
responsibilities at the time. But no, it
won't be a problem for us to continue
meeting during that that time period.
>> Good to go. Thank you.
>> Um so we'll probably start out bi-weekly
and uh you know roll out as as quickly
as as we can. Um, with the Department of
Health's accelerated timeline, feel like
we don't we can't procrastinate too
much. We need to really kind of hit the
ground running here. So, um, yeah.
Um,
I would like to come to consensus on
things as much as possible, you know,
but if I also want to encourage people
to speak up and don't be afraid to, you
know, go against the grain on on
something, we need to try to get this
right. And it takes all of us to be our
most courageous selves to to stand up
for what we know is true and right and
the best practices and what's going to
be best for New Mexico. So, I would like
you all to
um
to not shy away from conflict if we need
to have it. Sometimes it's necessary,
and I don't think it's something our
society typically deals with all that
well. Um, but I I'm willing to meet meet
you all and talk about this as many
times as we need to to kind of figure
out what's best for us. Um, and
so yeah, that's kind of where my thought
processes are right now. Um,
any questions or anybody think we should
make any changes to any of the the
bylaws that I've proposed.
>> Go ahead.
>> Apologies there. I just wanted to
quickly um state there was in the chat
um Gregory Evans simply uh just adding
to I think his introduction there um
just so it's on the spoken record uh he
wants to work to ensure propagation
framework includes all psilocybin
containing species not just cubes uh
regulations should accommodate exotic
species uh uh diversity. Yes.
>> Well and that's one of the things that
we're going to have to discuss. Yeah, I
I I tend to agree with you. Um, you
know, one thing we have working for us
here is that Colorado and Oregon have
obviously already done this, so we don't
have to reinvent the wheel. We can take
a lot of their products and and kind of
um
manipulate them to to fit what works for
New Mexico. Both of them, as far as I
understand, went with one. Okay. And you
I also need you all to understand that I
am on a steep learning curve here. I I
have grown some mushrooms on my kitchen
t some oyster mushrooms on my kitchen
table one time. But that is the extent
of my my ecology experience. So I've
been reading and learning. Um but I I'm
going to need you all's help about how
this is going to work. Okay. Um so
>> fantastic. We have a question or a hand
raised here by uh Denali. Uh Denali uh I
believe uh I've enabled your mic. Uh
when ready, please begin.
>> Hi chair. Um hi board and um department.
I just as you were asking about feedback
on the bylaws um a couple things jump
out at me. one. I think this is the
first bylaw committee um subcommittee
that I've seen a specific clause about
disruptive behavior. I think that's
smart and maybe the maybe the thing to
do is to add that to the full advisory
board um bylaws so that it's
consistently applied. And then I
mentioned in um in other bylaws that
we've been reviewing as subcommittees
are are meeting um that I I think it's
really um been consistent across the
board. Um the the and and is well
reasoned and makes a lot of sense and I
fully support the limitation of um
voting by um people who are um residents
of New Mexico. I think it's important to
to uh include ex include in that
exclusion um a a conflict of interest
clause and then maybe also a note about
anyone who's attending um as press. I I
don't know how frequent that would be at
least when the advisory board started
there. Um there was press and media. Um
but it might be helpful to include um
include clarification about those roles
and that those don't confer voting like
if you have a conflict or if you're um
you're attending as as media that that
would not confer voting right.
Oh,
>> I took bylaws from um Dr. Leman's
committee and I kind of modified them
from that.
>> Uh the reason I didn't add the
>> conflicted interest rule in there for
this is because I was assuming that a
lot of the people might be cultivators
in here and would naturally have a
conflict of interest. But since this any
recommendations this committee comes
with has to go through the board who
doesn't have conflict of interest, I I
figured that that would be our safeguard
against anything like that. Um, however,
if um we have a
large majority of people who think we
should add that back in, I am willing to
to do that. Dominic, yes, go ahead,
please.
>> Yeah, thank you, Chris. and and Denelli,
thank you. We did actually when you had
raised that previously, we did bring
that on up just to check and um
essentially what Chris is saying
regarding this not being a final
decision body, they're not necessarily
needed here. Um because uh at that
point, you know, the all of these
recommendations, this is really more of
a work group and all of those
recommendations will go to the board
where those exclusions are already there
based upon the fact that they're
appointed members and can't have those
conflicts and they are not media um uh
because that would be part of their
disclosures originally. Um, if this were
something more like the the board that
would be then making that recommendation
to the department, we would need to have
those exclusions in here and would have
those. But with them being working
groups, they're not necessary. But it is
up to this group to make that
determination. If it decides want to add
those on in, that is up to this group to
do. So, uh, just to to let everybody
know.
>> Fantastic. Thank you for that, Dominic.
Uh we have Desba there with their hand
up. Desb
your mic is enabled. So whenever you're
ready.
>> Hi. Yes. Thank you. Um I just kind of
wanted to put a a note on that with um
what Denali was saying. Um and then also
with this. Yeah, I really appreciate um
there's going to be I think a lot of uh
alignment with the rest of the
committees. I'm I'm wanting to safely
assume in how these are going to be
continued to govern, especially like in
mine. Um, and to that point, you know, I
think maybe what we're trying to look
for and acknowledge though with Denali's
point is the transparency of like where
these opinions and researching is coming
from. Um but I think that that's um
mainly you know again like the safeold
or the I'm not sure what the right
wording the safeold is is that it is it
is the committee I mean sorry it is the
board members when we are bringing these
voted matters from the committee to the
board to have a discussion that we are
aware that you know this the information
the suggestions the comments the
concerns may be coming from a place of I
don't want to in some ways conflict of
interest but not necessarily like
legally but mostly just you know we've
how many we are going to have a conflict
of interest where we're going to have
like one rule one rural propagation is
going to have an interest you know for
theirs versus some place in the city and
that's going to be a conflict of
interest but we are going to take those
into consideration when we're meeting um
together um as a board like how that's
going to look so I think it's really
important though to just make a note
that it is transparency um where
everyone's coming from their angles,
their concern and everyone does actually
have their own agenda. Um, and we
acknowledge that.
>> Thank you for that, Desba. Just to um
echo comments into the in the chat, we
have Denali there saying, "Thank you.
That makes a lot of sense to me. We need
the expertise of people who otherwise
may have a conflict. I think I agree
with that. Thanks for the conversation
on it. may be helpful to have uniformity
across subcommittees so expectations are
clear. Dominic then responds, "Exactly.
That is an important point to raise and
thank you for doing so." And finally, we
have James Brown uh who's saying,
"Hello, everyone. Sorry I was late to
the meeting." Back to you, Chris.
Okay, so did we clear up the concerns on
that or do do we feel like we need a
amendment of the bylaws?
Okay. If uh I think at this time I'm
going to ask for any dissent to adopting
these bylaws. And if there is none, then
we'll adopt these bylaws.
If you have disscent, go ahead and raise
your hand. Desp.
No, sorry. I just wanted to acknowledge
Donnie's last comment. I don't know if
we wanted to have a discussion on that.
>> Just to echo that. Um, she states, "I
agree with Desba. Disclosure is more
important than withholding from
influencing decisions. Perhaps the
clause should include a requirement that
parties with potential financial
interests in the program disclose those
interests as part of their
participation."
Um, I agree with that. Should we put
that in I I think I I kind of
um
>> I was I might Sorry, I'm jumping in and
sorry for the IT people. My mute is
still undone. So, I'm taking advantage
of that. I think actually and Dominic or
someone else can confirm this may be in
the original like the full bylaws of the
advisory board that covers this, right?
There was a statement of um that I think
um Alana from HCA recommended that we
include.
>> Yeah. So, and uh this is Dominic Denali.
We don't actually have to have it in the
committee bylaws similar to the others
because it because this is not a final
recommendation and it has to go to the
board. Um you can have that. However, as
the committee does move forward, one of
the things that I think would be
beneficial for it is when there are some
of those large decisions is asking at
that time, are there individuals who
have potential conflicts? And just to
have them state that they have those
those potential financial or other
conflicts, but it doesn't need to
necessarily be within the bylaws
themselves. Again, this is more of a
working group and so it doesn't need to
necessarily be as formal as a an actual
advisory board. So that can be done as
necessary and as needed if that makes
sense. And if not I can explain a little
more.
>> I I think we could also um just put a
another
um comment into article five
um
saying that any voting member needs to
have the to express their conflicts of
interest.
Um, there might be a better way to put
that.
>> And uh, just to let you know, we have a
hand up there by Evans, Gregory Evans.
So, uh, yeah, I think your mic is still
uh, enabled. So, whenever you're ready,
>> go ahead, Greg.
>> Free mic button.
Um [clears throat]
on this point um I think it's vitally
important that we have industry
professionals in the room people who are
going to be standing up largecale
projects anybody who is going to be
contributing to software development for
compliance software like those people
need to be in this room and if they are
not we need to bring them in. I know of
a handful of people that might be shy to
show up to something like this and we
need to make them feel welcome because
though the input of people that have
been doing this work on scale for a
period of time under whatever
context they may have been doing that u
will have a lot of information to
provide us. There are some major
mistakes that Colorado and especially
Oregon have made and some of those are
because people are making decisions
about
research they don't understand.
Specifically, they banned wood lovers.
Now, nobody can grow anything that grows
on wood and that would also mean that
you can't grow lion's mate. Um,
[clears throat] and so I think that
there is a lot of sanity that needs to
be brought to these conversations.
um those people don't necessarily need
to vote on what's passed to the advisory
board, but
uh we want the experience of people who
are going to be uh standing up the
industry.
That's all I have.
>> I 100% agree and like I expressed
before, I do not know everything I need
to know uh to to make these
recommendations. So, I'm going to be
relying on on a lot of the people in
this room. And if there's people we need
to track down and I need to go invite to
come to these committee meetings
personally, let me know and I I will I
will uh go buy him a cup of coffee or do
whatever I need to do to make that
happen.
>> Fantastic. We have a few comments in the
chat. Um Desba there saying that uh I
concur with Dominic's point. Taye saying
I agree with Dominic. Denali. Uh that
seems like a good practice. And Dominic
there um saying stating that he has
added um this as language. Any
individual voting uh needs to express uh
conflict of interest during a vote on
the request of the chair. Um and next
there we have James with their hands up.
James, I've allowed your mic. When
you're ready, please begin.
>> Yeah. Hi everybody. I'd like to
introduce myself. I've been to several
of these committee meetings. My name is
James Ferrer. That's how you pronounce
that last name. Uh I am a software
developer and have also previously I was
the CIO at the attorney general's office
under Gary King and um also have had six
years of experience at Google uh
producing software and AI and I have
actually started producing software for
this effort uh which I will share the
website ignitesergy.com. I am looking
for uh input from everybody across the
spectrum. The software covers everything
from genetics management and the process
of growing mushrooms uh being able to
track all your grain bags and your
substrate bags and production all those
things uh feeding into a network that
handles providers and all the way
through to patient long-term outcomes.
So, um, looking for lots of feedback,
but I'll continue to join these meetings
and add all of the different, um, uh,
you know, requirements that would be
needed in a software like this.
>> Thank you for that. And we just have a
comment in the chat there. Did James say
is the question?
We have an answer there. ignite energy
and uh David asking can you repeat the
website?
>> Yeah, let me just uh throw it right here
in the chat. [snorts]
>> Fantastic. Thank you very much for that.
>> Thank you, James.
Okay. Are there any other um issues with
the bylaws?
Last chance.
All right. Seeing no other dissent to
the bylaws, will adopt these bylaws as
amended.
And I think next we need to move on to
uh kind of the expanded scope
of the propagation committee that I've
I've kind of come up with
and I'm getting that switching screens
on that for you Chris. In the meantime,
while it takes a moment for the system
to catch up, just want to let everybody
know that the documents that are agreed
on during this will be posted to the
website. Um, however, as we've been
saying in the other meetings, oh, and I
should say as well as the recording of
this meeting. Um, however, it can take a
between 5 to 10 business days for
everything to get up on the website. So,
please be uh mindful of that. We will
get it as soon as possible. It's usually
less than that, but um we do have to
submit it into for review and to our IT.
Um, and so as soon as that has occurred,
then uh we will get it posted and uh you
should all be able to see the new
document. I'm just expanding it on out
for everybody.
Can people see it? Head not or yes.
Yes. Okay, great. Thank you everybody.
And I am going to put the text in the
chat so that as Chris goes through it,
you don't you don't have to read every
line, Chris. So, thanks.
>> I'll have that for you in just a moment.
All right, there you go. It is also in
the chat now. So, back to you, Chris.
>> Okay, so
um like I said, there's a lot I don't
know in here. So, I'm kind of flying by
the seat of my pants uh and and working
with what I have, what I've seen from
Colorado, some of their u questions they
were asking, some of the the um
recommendations they made and uh I I
basically stole some of that and kind of
came up with this list of things that we
got to come up with. Um, like I said
before, what the board kind of
authorized this committee to do was very
vague and in four bullet points. Um, but
it's definitely going to be more in
depth than that, I think. And and so and
also probably a little bit more
expanded. I was looking at at how
um the work kind of got divvied out and
I and I feel like we're gonna have to
deal with cultivation, production or
testing, production, and probably
distribution, too. Uh it seems logical
that that would fall into this
committee. So, basically everything from
growing the mushrooms to getting the
mushrooms into the hand of the
facilitator and then, you know, we're
we're kind of done. Um,
is there any questions on that so far?
Okay.
Um,
so
like I said, I don't know all the the
questions that we need to ask. So, if
people think that we need to add
sections here, um like I I have uh very
limited experience with the software
that's going to be needed to track the
genealogy and all of this stuff. You
guys are talking light years ahead of
where I'm at right now. Um so,
please feel free to add recommendations
to this. This is um just a document I I
came up with to kind of give us a broad
overview of what we're trying to
accomplish here. Um
so as far as cultivation goes,
um
feel like
this isn't probably not even expanded
enough. We we're also going to have to
figure out everything from what kind of
um mushrooms we're going to grow,
uh
what substrates we can use, hygiene
protocols, all of that type of stuff,
right? Um,
I don't know if anybody can speak from
experience on this, but or from
knowledge on this, but uh, Colorado and
Oregon are both only using cub cubensus
strains. Is that correct?
>> And does anybody know why?
>> Yeah, I can actually speak a little bit
to that, Chris. So um part of the reason
for limiting to a particular uh group so
to speak is because it is very difficult
otherwise to be able to track and ensure
that there is consistency in the
quality. Now that doesn't necessarily
mean that it cannot be done. It's just
from what I have heard from those
regulators that is one of the primary
reasons behind why they have only used
the cubensus.
>> Yep. And as Greg put down testing
testing testing that is one of the most
important aspects of it.
>> Yeah, I agree. However, the more testing
we have, the more expensive our product
becomes and the less accessible. Right,
Greg? Go ahead.
>> Uh, Greg, I've just enabled your mic. I
apologize for that. Do you want to go
ahead
>> the whole thing?
Um there are emerging technologies that
will allow for like a greater access to
testing. Um we already do batch testing
in cannabis and it's not pro cost
prohibitive you know. Um,
[clears throat]
I think we're doing ourselves a
disservice going into medical only
without allowing ourselves to really
understand the depth of potential with
this medicine. And
for example, say we have a client that
has IBS, can't really eat five grams of
mushrooms. You give them a half a gram
of panel essence and they're good to go.
like that person wouldn't be able to
access those deeper levels of this
medicine because of gut veagal issues,
digestion issues, other things like
that. So,
I think we have enough time to figure it
out. Um, if we got to figure out how to
put money into research systems that are
leveraged for testing,
pull independent financers into fund
operations that just make sure that
everything is tested. I mean, like, just
go ask people for money. I know that I
know of $100,000.
Is it 10,000 that Lima has offered? the
Limina has a bunch of money that they
want to just give
this program to succeed, right? So,
there's [clears throat] other there
there are ways that that m funds can be
funneled into equity and access. Um, hi
Desba.
Um, but yeah,
thank you very much for that. Uh, Desba,
I will get to you in just a second. Can
I just have a few comments in the chat
there? Uh first is uh Denali. I also
believe it may be because that it is the
species that has the most research
around. Uh James then um points out that
they are very consistent to grow. Denali
then says uh but encourage the
conversation about whether it makes
sense to limit here in the same way.
Important early conversation. Uh Desba I
have enabled your mic. When ready please
begin.
Yeah, I think that this is starting a
good point where, you know, what are we
establishing to Greg's to Greg's point,
um, what are the, you know, one or two
or three species that we're going to
look at, you know, like the Goldilocks,
right, as far as like the baby bear, the
big bear, and the mama bear. What is it
that would look like that would be best
suitable for, you know, New Mexicans? Is
it going to be the same thing? are we
looking at to kind of to Greg's point
which I think is a valid point to look
at. Um but then also too you know kind
of um what those um what are people
already
maybe this is asking too much and too
implicating what are people already
growing that they've had the most
successful you know in their own homes
or that they are aware of that have been
more successful in their own homes. Um
but also too what would be the most cost
effective and also which brings into um
conversation the New Mexico growers um
because I as far as I know uh and
understand it's going to be limited to
New Mexico growers and then that comes
into the certification process of
whether how that how that looks is this
like slapping on a New Mexico True sort
of uh certification for the growers here
um that are already starting to
cultivate and so forth. But then again,
looping back into the research of which
one, you know, um we see and have been
aware of is has been the most successful
um on our own um in in that way. Um but
I think it's a really good a good
starting point of like what what does
New Mexico need? What has seemed to be
like the most researched thing that
could potentially be, you know, better
for micro doing, better for the heroic
dose? But then that goes back into IN's
committee with the dosage. So I think
it's a good um kind of spiraling point
to figure out like where are we starting
um creating that framework.
>> Yeah. Um I agree. Go ahead again, Greg.
You can jump back in.
And Greg, uh, your mic is enabled. Go on
ahead and, uh, uh, you can start
speaking again.
>> Yeah. And like
Chris, back to your earlier comment
about, um, you know, uh, being
challenging or whatever, like slow me
down if I'm saying too much. Um, because
I will have the tendency to talk. I have
a lot of information that I haven't
really been able to share with a lot of
people just because of the nature of
this this work. Um I have cultivated
without ever harvesting or drying
uh several species. Um and and I think
one of the things that we need to
understand and please if any of the
other cultivators in this room can
piggyback off some of this. I don't want
to be the only voice of information
here. Um but yeah in
micological taxonomy we have
species genus and species we have clades
inside those species inside each species
we'll have clades and then inside clades
will have kind of like sections right so
there is a section zaporum inside
section zaporum you will find things
like In gi from South Africa, you will
find uh [clears throat]
seerviva HVC which is not really like a
hooch ganini um but is like commonly
referred to as hushkani var combeexa um
we'll have zaporum from this region
zaporum from this region and because of
the way that taxonomists
identify things those become different
species. And sometimes they're lumped
together, sometimes they are realled.
Um, and yes, Eric,
centrada, not in section zaporum,
although um, [clears throat] I was going
to get to occasio centrada in a minute.
Um,
the likeio centrada for a time was
thought to be a cubensus. It's about 2
and a half million years older than
cubensus, easier to cultivate, twice as
potent as highly cultivated mutated
cubensus strains and has
anti-inflammatory properties that
improve gut veagal performance. So
I think that we are simply
not maximizing our potential to change
the freaking world if we are just going
to sell Jedi mind to people that have
never
seen a mushroom or have any
understanding of its p uh potential. Um
but yeah, open species I will
freedom to grow anything would like
within certain guard rails would be my
um I will soapbox that and I will annoy
people until it happens. Um but also
it's about education. Like if anybody
wants to sit down and learn about wood
lovers paralysis, I can get
the guy who's doing the research in
Australia on the phone to talk to us
about un unpublished work um around
suburaginosa
which is the species that
uh turned like has traveled around the
world and become a
wood loving species. There's Indian wood
lovers. There's all kinds of stuff
across Europe and North America. Um,
[clears throat] and that those are the
those are the philosophies that have a
concern for a par paralytic effect that
is non-damaging and probably potentiated
by unknown chemicals that we're not
testing for.
Anyhow,
keep it open.
Okay,
>> that's my vote.
>> One thing, Greg, please in the future,
um, be mindful of your language. We're
trying to post these, uh, so they can be
publicly accessible. And once we use,
um,
certain language on on these videos,
then we can we can no longer post them.
If is that correct, Dominic?
>> Uh, it is. And and I will say that I do
understand that actually is a strain, a
particular name for a mushroom. So I
think we'll be okay on this, but I would
ask in the future when we have names
that do include um common cuss words
that we actually change it to the
abbreviations just so that we don't run
into any issues with being able to post
it. But we do understand it occurs on
occasion. Uh but thank you very much.
Thank you for that. Uh Desbel, you have
your hand up. Um please, uh I believe uh
I've enabled your mic when ready.
>> Yep. Sorry. [laughter]
Um, Chris, I think that like again back
to Greg's point, um, to me what it
sounds like also is as a starting point
for discussion for this group, um, that
we we remember that there are
opportunities and I don't want to say
back doors, but um, to how the research
for other species might be available
with the intention of, you know, looking
at what this looks like for the future
of medical use. Um I know I know we are
we have our opinions on how we feel like
the psilocybin should be used and for
what purposes but we also have to be
mindful um that you know we are given
this framework and it's you know for
medical uh use and for trials and um so
that's what we're starting with and it
doesn't mean at least in my
understanding that we can't have
opportunities for further study and
research and use but at this point it is
it is strictly for medical and how does
anything that we are proposing or
recommending suggesting um return to
that return to the definition of of the
framework that we're trying to move this
forward. So yes, where it might be open
for more species for research for
medical use in the future. Um back to
the idea of you know what is the equity
not just for
uh the uh patients but also for the
cultivators. What is the most equitable
for growing for allowing um you know is
it is it grants? Is it subsidies? Is it
loans? What does it look like to be able
to have access? You know, back to my
committee for for the cultivators. What
is the most um common species or strain
that we could possibly use? Um and or
one or two. What does that look like?
Um, and it's something that can be
easily um accessible to anyone and who
can um, you know, whether it's in Mora
or or Clayton, Raton, Los Cusus, Santa
Fe, you know, it should definitely be
able to be accessible and and grown
easily in some ways for for those who
are creating the medicine.
>> Thank you very much for that. Um, and we
have some comments in the chat. Um, Eric
with a term that I will will not attempt
to uh pronounce, but it's a very long
word there. Anyone else knows how to
pronounce that? I will go for it. Uh, we
also have a we should keep the species
open. Exactly. Then research can be
done. Well stated. Brenda then uh says,
"I think we need to have as many species
as possible." James [snorts]
then responds with uh fresh and dried is
also an interesting discussion point. Um
Evans, so Gregory then says, "Copy."
Yes, JMF, sorry. Uh, that is uh the
federally approved cultiv cultivar grown
in Arizona by Sue and apologies for that
language slip up. And Estavan, regarding
non-Cubanese species, um, where would
liability on adverse experiences be
placed, uh, the cultivator, the
practitioner, or the state? Um, I'll let
someone answer that before I continue
with the next comments uh, in the chat.
Anyone have any
>> Ishmael? That is a good question and uh
it actually would end up going to either
and I don't know the answer on this, the
cultivator or the practitioner.
>> Fantastic. Thank you for that. Uh
Maximleian then says psilocybin, another
term I will not attempt to pronounce,
but uh is a strain worth considering
utilizing as a starting point as it is
native to New Mexico, but keeping the
species open is important. Okrao
Centrata.
Thank you. Thank you for that.
[laughter]
Much appreciated.
Yeah, I think that's a interesting
starting point to kind of kick that off.
And um I think cultivation,
you know, I I think we kind of got ahead
of ourselves. I meant to kind of just go
through the big bullet points on this
list and talk about all the different
things that we're probably going to need
to accomplish in the next um six eight
months. I do have one quick question for
Dominic. when we uh when the board
approves a set of recommendations to uh
the department of health, then you guys
are going to have to take those and
put them into some sort of rule and
legally ease it up, I would imagine.
Right. Um how long is that process going
to take?
>> So it depends on the length and the
complexity of the recommendations and
the rule. Um and um so we we will take
those different pieces. But as I've kind
of said during the board uh some of the
the main board meetings is that one of
the things with this change in the
timeline is remember that the initial
launch is not going to be the full
program. So, for example, as we're
talking about keeping different species
open, things like that, if that is
something that is a recommendation down
the road, that may not necessarily be a
part of the initial rules simply so that
we can get the program started to have
some patients be seen by that December
time frame. The rulem process is not a
static process. it can it will continue
to go on not even just for the next two
years probably for three or four quite
frankly which is what we see in other
areas. And so that allows for some of
these other areas to also open up um if
in the initial stage because it will be
limited in some ways because it won't be
the full program yet. Um, so we have to
say for example, how much testing will
there be? If there's not the capacity to
be able to have lots of different
species, it may need to be limited
initially and then as that
infrastructure grows, then that can open
up as an example. But the exact length
of time, uh, we usually turn things
around fairly quickly, um, you know,
within a few weeks to month. But the
part that actually slows it down the
most, and it's not a bad thing, it's
actually can be a good thing, is the
public comment because we want to make
sure that we're getting that comment,
that we're including everything that we
possibly can at that time into it. But
also remember, we're not always going to
be include
everything. Um, but that there'll be
multiple rule hearings, multiple
changes, additions, addendums to the
rules until we actually do have the full
program. And even then, just as an
example, I mean, we have had medical
cannabis for uh it's almost 20 years
now, not quite, but almost. And we even
had a rulemaking process for that back
in 2022. So, give you an example. It
just keeps going on because as the
research also gets better, we have more
information. We may need to change some
of that. So, please keep that in mind.
the initial rules are not going to be
the final the the program is locked into
that forever. So just remember that um
the idea here is safety get things
moving forward and then as we have to
pivot because no matter how good we do
and no matter how good there you can you
tell I'll tell it's a long day and it's
a Friday afternoon how well we do um
with regard to creating them there are
going to be things that we need to
change and we need to recognize our
humanity in that and we need to be also
ready to pivot when we find that there
are things that need to be changed and
so our our most important aspect is
safety especially in the beginning and
so that safety aspect may mean things
need to be a little limited in those
initial rules with the understanding
that we are going to be expanding things
as there's more expertise infrastructure
and ability in the state to be able to
do things I hope that helps and I hope I
didn't confuse things more
>> no I think that that helps a a lot, but
it's still even for a limited roll out,
we it seems like we have to get a lot of
work done in probably the next nine
months or maybe even a little sooner.
Um,
so I I I appreciate that um update and
let's just go through the major bullets
here of what I was kind of thinking that
we need to to get done. I think we we
covered the cultivation quite a bit. Um,
can you scroll back up to B? So, um,
yeah, testing quality and laboratory
standards is going to be, um, going hand
inand with that cultivation piece a lot.
How we're going to test those, what I
don't know what kind of contaminants we
need to test for, how often we need to
do all that type of stuff. This is all
all things that we're going to have to
recommend. Um,
and then what are we allowed to do with
that whole mushroom after
we've grown it? Can we,
you know,
turn it into various products for
consumption? um or
are we
um and how you know
what are the limits that we're going to
allow people to do extractions and other
things? Um scroll down a little bit
please.
How do we package it? How do we get it
to the facilitators?
All of these questions I think need to
be asked. But again, we we don't need
need to recreate the wheel here. I think
some of this we can probably steal from
marijuana. Some of it we can steal from
Colorado. Um moving these products
around shouldn't be too difficult.
But how do our licenses work? What kind
of standards we have to abide by? And uh
I think we covered to some of the
affordability, access and uh other
considerations.
Um
yeah. Uh I think these next bullets are
kind of
um
what
Dominic was talking about and this is
going to be an ongoing thing, right?
We're going to continue uh continue
developing this as time goes on and uh
that is gonna
>> we have a question in the chat uh there.
Sorry about that. Just wanted to quickly
uh by Ben uh if we're looking at
psilocyb species cuminis or and
otherwise wouldn't the potency and
contamination testing be done with the
same equipment? That's a question there.
If anyone has an answer,
Gregory uh answering that not
necessarily. So there we have it.
Um,
but I think our priority for the next
couple meetings is going to need to
start, you know, at the surface level
where we cultivate and what we're
cultivating. So, I think this um
this conversation about what strains
we're going to use and
uh if somebody could help me out, what
terminology should I actually be saying
here? What genus we're going to open up
to? Is uh cubensus a a genus or is it Go
ahead, Craig.
>> I'm here for you, man. Um and we should
we should do a lot of talking.
[clears throat]
Dominic, I sent an email to that from
the earlier meeting today. inside there
there is a glossery of terms. Um feel
free to review and redline it and make
something out of it. But um
[clears throat]
I will stand on a soap box and ask that
we not use the term strain.
Um
we have cultivars.
So inside Cubensus, our
tidal wave, our nerds, our
whatever funny name somebody gives a
thing that is an isolation. Those would
be cultivars all in the same species.
Salosby is a genus. Pineelius is a
genus. There are a small a number of
other genuses that produce psilocybin
containing mushrooms but those are the
two main ones. Um inside
salosity you have species such as
cubensus meascularis
okraioentrada
etc etc. So it maybe we put it on the
genus level and say we can cultivate
saloses and maybe we redline certain
species and we can cultivate panelius.
I don't panos I don't know if I'm
pronouncing that one right.
Uh does that answer your question Chris
question Chris?
>> Yes. So, no strain. So, stick with u
>> I mean that's that's my
that's my uh I don't know I'm not the
only one but yeah I would I would
encourage that to adopt that language.
It's wrong for fungal
identifications. It's also wrong for
biological. So people use it in
cannabis. We're not going to stop them
from doing it. We're never going to
change the way that people are speaking
about it. But, you know, maybe if we
start correct here.
>> Okay, sounds good. I'm I'm down with
that. Um, and then maybe I can get you
to send me that same document you sent,
Dominic, so I can take a look at kind of
what you're going for. But my my guess
is uh on cultivation
um maybe we could open it up a little
bit but but maybe not give it the full
um the full reign of all salosi
mushrooms
um
to start with um but again I think that
might be a discussion for our next uh
eating.
Uh Eric Baka says, "Why not?" Well,
based on what we were just talking about
with with the safety practices, is it is
it going to be a problem to open it up
to all saloscopy species? Let's just uh
let's open that up for discussion,
please. Does anybody have safety
concerns?
And then recognizing that that is going
to be
the
um
I I'm sorry I lost my train of thought.
Go ahead, Desbon.
>> I've enabled your mic.
>> Okay. Um,
granted I am also not um that versed on
on this. And again, back to the idea
that this is specifically and and I'm
I'm happy to have anyone argue this
point like the full the full definition
of argue. Um, this is specifically for
medical use within the framework. Not
necessarily that like
and as a scientist from a scientist
perspective, the the fewer uh cultverse
or starting point that we have, then the
better quote control that we might be
able to have when it comes to the
dosaging, the research, the money that's
involved in financing. If we're
financing several different um forgive
me Greg species that you know like all
all of them that's that's great but we
need to be careful into one of the
reasons why I probably picked one is
especially for that for efficiency
for uh scientific control for
understanding you know putting it into
that particular
um
and I Well, Greg, that's great. But, um,
it's not so much limited to not having
the research for other things. That's
there's two different points here.
Finding the research open for different
species is not is is one discussion
which again would be for the re research
committee.
What we're looking at is specific places
where what does this look like for this
specifically in in in different ways for
the cultivators what can be grown and
what that looks like but also
specifically for medical use research
there has to be a streamline I guess
that's what I'm trying to say the
streamline what does the streamline look
from one cultivator to the um admin to
the facilitator
to the patient back to research back to
there has to be as far as like a
scientific looking at it like one flow
in that way does not mean that that
excludes the research of looking into
other things to me there's two different
points and I just to me that's kind of
what the clarity I feel like um when we
start getting into the weeds of why not
all it's not so much why not all all of
them are beneficial just the same way as
we all are points the view are
beneficial. But what we're looking at
under a microscope one particular thing,
how do how do we the chain of command
for that one particular thing and or
two, what does that look like from cult
uh from cultivation down to the patient
and then back up again to the research.
That's the only thing is like just
understanding the clarity of what we're
actually trying to define the framework
and the structure of how we're looking
at um regulating.
>> Thank you very much for that. We have
Ben there with their hand raised. I've
enabled your mic when you're ready.
>> Yeah, thank you. I think those are good
points, Desba. Um, I think we could look
at also whether we're going to accept
cultivars that are genetically sequenced
or have had cellular manipulation or
what degree of hybridizing. I think we
could kind of agree on some parameters
of what's important culturally.
And to me that also includes adaptation.
What is indigenous to this place? uh
what are uh heirloom and and heritage
cultivars that go back to to Waka to
Maria Sabina to the indigenous people uh
that kept these traditions going for a
long time. I I think that there's some
importance in clarifying that and
keeping it an open path towards the
research and and towards uh other other
kinds of mushrooms as well. It's my
input.
Yeah. Um
I think
kind of hearing a a mix here. I feel
like
um
you know the growers and the
facilitators knowing that they're going
to be the ones accountable for any
mishaps that go on with you know a non
mainstream
mushroom.
um
will probably help some of
uh
um
will help people, you know, I guess
choose better options, but
I I I think that leaves a lot of room
for
error. Um,
I'm sorry. I'm kind of looking at the
chat here, too.
But maybe we should uh sit on the the
species type for this the rest of this
session. And and what other cultivation
um
issues are we going to bring up? And um
what kind of things do we need to look
at in the cultivation process?
None of my cultivators have any any
concerns or
um I recently learned about the the MGAP
practices
set forth by the USDA.
Um, [clears throat] and is that kind of
the standard that you all go by and or
is there a higher standard that we
should use or that I should look into
and get familiar with?
Just uh outlining one question there by
James. Just uh seems like a clear
question. Um I may have missed it, but I
believe explicit good manufacturing
practice language should be incorporated
into the bylaws to ensure that
cultivation, production, and handling of
psilocybin meet safety quality
standards. More of a point rather than a
question. My apologies.
Yeah, James. Uh, uh, I think the good
manufacturing practices will come out of
the recommendations and it won't
necessarily uh be governed by the
bylaws. The bylaws are just kind of
governing the the behavior and how this
committee can uh
conducts its affairs. So hopefully those
good manufacturing practices come out of
our recommendations and we can
um
yeah we can give those to the board who
will then vote on them and send them to
the department of health.
All right. Um so I think James is
bringing up a good point here. We need
security requirements. Uh we need to
think about that through all stages of
the process, right? Like what kind of
security do we need to have on our grow
operations and where is it stored? Uh it
some of this will probably come in
different
uh sections of our um or different
committees as far as storage. Once it
gets to the facilitator, I'm not worried
about it.
Um,
but there's a lot of in between.
I got another question for the producers
or the cultivators. Is
um production going to be something that
we're going to be seeing are cultivators
do or are you all planning on turning
these the dry mushroom into various
products? And if so, what kind of
products and what should we not allow?
Um,
>> I'm not getting a lot of bites here.
>> Chris, I think from the silence they
think we should create all products.
>> All products. [laughter] what products
are available?
>> No, but I think it's a really great
question um because you know there and
and as we talk with um different um
current producers um whether it be in
Oregon, Colorado um and also not
necessarily through um listenit or
standardized sources. you know, as Eric
actually says is yes, you can basically
make any edible products, but there are
a few things to consider. When you start
looking at items for food manufacturing,
it starts to fall under some other
federal requirements and regulations.
And it's actually part of the reason why
there were so many issues with regard to
cannabis branching out into other types
of products initially. that is going to
take some different time or or I'm sorry
that is going to say take some
additional effort and time to be able to
ensure that additional products could
potentially be made and we also have to
think about it from a standpoint of
making sure things are done um in a
consistent way and uh so I see Estabbon
does has put in value added products are
on the table for a significant amount of
growers and the cost viability is really
the issue there is because they're it
can be prohibitive to get the um the
equipment the inspections that are
needed and uh you know the um they often
consider things that are schedule one to
be um to be contaminant and so that
creates additional issues with regard to
food products and that is again exactly
the problem that we ran into with
cannabis. And so um in the very
beginning at least as we are working on
those other areas looking at things for
example as David in the chat has said
looking at whole mushrooms but also
trying to figure out how do we actually
make this so that we can get
standardized dosing because since this
is looking at it from a medication
standpoint we need to see about doing
that so it is standardized and so when
we look at types of products we also
have to make sure that the products can
be standardized because otherwise your
testing issue is going to be part of
what really comes into play because how
do you then test for example and just
because it's there in the chat how do
you then test each individual chocolate?
How do you test those? How do you figure
out the batching system for it? And so
remembering that those add additional
items have to be considered as you move
forward when you create additional
products because anybody who does baking
can tell you and and most of you I'm
sure you've done that. You get a brownie
and you find that there's a clump of
flour in it or a clump of something
else. And so how do you ensure then when
those other productions are being done
that you turn around and actually make
uh a standardized process or a
standardized dosing amount within each
of those food items. So these are things
to really talk about um with regard uh
with regard um to that sort of creating
those extra products. Um and so in the
initial stages we do need to think about
looking at it while those barriers and
those potential problems can be
resolved. Looking at it from that whole
mushroom and standardization aspect and
again not to say that there there isn't
the room to look at those items as we
continue moving forward but how do we
start out from the very beginning and we
do have to make sure that items are
standardized so that uh they are there.
sack just to let you know um you have
the question there about facilities
produced medicine be allowed to produce
non-medical product I'm not sure if you
mean non-medical psilocybin
uh non-medicals psilocybin is not
allowed under the statute so the answer
to that would be no if you mean other
products for example um you know just
creating other products so if they're
making chocolate that's just chocolate
again that's one of the issues where the
FDA and some of those other food
handling
concerns come in. And that was one of
the big issues we did run into with
cannabis, especially in the very
beginning where they could not even get
licenses to be able to do food handling
um in order to be able to do that. And
uh so Zach, that's why I just wanted to
let you know with regard to that. Um so
it depends on what you mean when you're
asking about non-medical products. Um,
but we do want to make sure that places
are able to do this uh in in a
cost-effective way and in a way that
they're going to be able to survive.
It's one of the things we have heard
time and time again that um uh that the
cost is one of the biggest issues and so
we need to make sure that we keep that
cost down and that people are going to
be able to afford the medicine aspects
of it.
Um, and Max Millan includes in there,
and uh, that's part of what I was trying
to get to, Max Millan, is capsules,
tinctures, less disruptive, easier
consumption, and standardization. So,
thank you for expressing that in the
chat. And, uh, I'm not going to read all
the comments about Zach. U, uh, but
Zach, yes, it'd be great if you were the
director. We might be able to talk with
you about some of the other film issues
going on. But, uh, you know, very nice
to, uh, have you here even or regardless
of your connections or no connections to
the film industry. So, thank you. And as
you can tell, we're not always serious
here as well.
Yeah, Maximillian, I agree. Uh, capsules
and tinctures might be easier for
consumption. Um,
but you know, how how are those
tinctures made? how what extraction
techniques are we going to allow? I
think that's another question that comes
up um from that
and um does that add another level of
testing as well when we do that? Do we
do we have to do they have to test the
dry mushroom and then test the tincture?
Um is that how that would work, Dominic,
or would they be able to make the
tincture and then have the tincture
tested?
Well, that that is part of the question
as well. And some of the things with
regard to cannabis is well and actually
this is just within food production
overall. Every time you go through a new
process, you actually have the
possibility to add contaminants. And so
you have to make that decision and
that's a part of what the program will
have to decide and the recommendations
from the board and and this committee is
what is an acceptable level of risk with
regard to things like contaminants. So,
for example, if you test that tincture
or or you're testing an extraction of
some kind and then you turn around and
you actually add it into a uh and I'm
just going to say a chocolate making
process. You have all that equipment
that is being used in that chocolate
making process. How do you ensure that
that is contaminant-free that there
aren't any issues? So then you would to
be make that to have that uh that
assurance at the end of it you would
then have to test at least a sampling of
those end products and that's actually
what does happen in food manufacturing.
there are testing points throughout and
being able to have to do that and that's
that's some of what we are getting here
um within the chat is talking about some
of the consistent do doses homogenizing
it um testing the batches and doing that
but every step of the way you have to
think about where contaminants could
potentially come in and so what then is
the appropriate level of testing without
having to test at every single point
because doing that is what would
actually drive the cost up um to a point
where it would not be um would not
actually be able to be done. And um and
as Greg brings up, then you also have
the question of can the labs actually
test a finished product versus uh the
extraction. And so that's another aspect
there that um we talk a lot about um you
know where exactly we do the testing.
And if you think about it from a
standpoint of uh of a company that is
actually producing this and from their
standpoint, if you do not have test
points, even if they are not required by
the program, if you do not have test
points within the process itself during
the cultivation and then the
manufacturing of products, you actually
run the risk of going all the way from,
you know, the initial growth all the way
to an end product and then the end
product ending up being contaminated.
and you know have no idea where in that
chain that contamination occurred. It
could have been in the last step. It
could have been in an early step. And so
they as part of their business process
are going to be wanting to be doing
testing throughout so that they're not
actually wasting time, product, energy,
and effort in something that potentially
would be contaminated because it had
contamination in an early step. And so
from a cost-effective standpoint, there
is this balance and that's some of what
we need to determine is what do we
require from a program standpoint and
what will the the organizations that are
doing the cultivators what will they be
doing just as a part of their normal
business practice and is that is
something that we have to actually
require and so that's where part of that
balance comes in some ways we could
simply do and dement or Bez mentions it
is we could just require end product
testing
and that could be something that could
be done as far as the program. It would
be a little bit less of regulatory
oversight but it would require that that
um that final test so that no matter
what before the product goes to the
patient that it has been tested and that
it is contaminant free um and that it is
safe for that patient. But that may
create some issues for the cultivator um
to because they may need to do things at
other earlier points from their own
perspective to be able to say we need to
ensure that this product is not costing
us money with potential contaminants
somewhere else in the line.
I know that's a lot of information and a
lot of people throwing things in the
chat, but uh these are some of the some
of the areas and things that need to be
considered with regard to this.
>> Yeah, that makes sense. I I think um
I'm not sure about Colorado's product
testing, but you know, for what they're
doing as far as uh their batch testing,
it it seems like they're just
homogenizing a batch and doing psilocin
and psilocybin content testing that
needs to be redone after, I believe,
nine months.
One thing that they had in there was
that if the the second test after nine
months comes out
with a higher content than the first
um that they have to
destroy that product. Can anybody
explain that to me why that is?
Anybody
have any theories?
Right.
We have one hand up there. Brett,
let's allow your mic when you're ready.
Hey. Yeah, thanks guys. Um, so I'm not a
I'm not a scientist or cultivator, but
my general understanding
um is that the potency should go should
theoretically go down over time. And so
they they probably would assume that
there's something wrong happened in the
first batch if somehow you test it nine
months later and it's now testing
stronger. Um, I think that would just go
against the the general science of how
that works and it's something they
probably decided was not worth taking a
risk on that the the first test couldn't
be considered trusted, I guess. And I
don't know if maybe you could run a
second test on your second batch because
maybe it was that one that was messed
up, but yeah, that would be my my theory
as to why that would be the the process
there.
Yeah, I think the potency
will go down over time. That's how I
understand it. Um, and I, you know, this
batch testing,
no matter how well we homogenize these
batches, I I feel like there's always
going to be some variability from dose
to dose in there. So, it could just be
in that situation. It could just be
that, you know, you got a low dose
uh that you tested in the first part and
then you end up with a high dose and the
the second one now you got to throw away
a whole batch. Just didn't really make
sense to me. Um Greg, maybe you could
shed some light on it for me.
>> Go right ahead. Your microphone has been
enabled.
>> Thank you. Um
it depends on like how we define batch.
So if we define a batch as one pound of
mushrooms that was inoculated
and moved to fruing on the same date. A
batch that's very different than each
bag.
Say we have five pound bags on a shelf
and we have a batch that has 30 bags.
If each of those bags has to have its
own test, that's a different cost.
>> [clears throat]
>> I can tell you that if I take one six C
shoe box and grow,
you know, harvest 300 g wet
of
whatever that inside that 300 grams when
it dries down it'll be 30 g. Um,
theoretically, not that I've ever
participated in that type of behavior
outside of DC. Um, [clears throat]
inside that 30 grams, if you test one
mushroom, it can be massively different
potency from another mushroom,
especially if it is like say an abort or
a smaller mushroom that hasn't fully
matured. um or has not. So basically
when the mushrooms mature in their
growth cycle, they'll hit there's like a
point in growth where they have max
potency per biomass weight
and not all fruing bodies in the same
flush are going to be equal. So like if
you take
all 10 pounds of your harvest, right,
and then you grind those in a flower
mill,
then you will have a relatively
even homogenization of
that batch. where if you test say you
your your analytics lab is going to take
five random samples from that and see if
they all kind of come out relatively
similar and then you could get a range
or like hopefully a very accurate uh
representation of that mass. But if you
have 10 pounds of non homogenized
mushrooms, individual mushrooms, each
one of those can needs it needs to be
understood that that will be in a
variable range. It's very difficult to
specify
like that is a very real question and
problem that we're going to have to like
address.
Thanks, Greg. Dave,
um, did you have something to add?
Thanks for coming, Dave.
We have a question there by James.
Go right ahead.
>> Yeah. I was say it in the tracking. One
of the the parts that I I find difficult
to to put in there is if you're working
with just one, you know, one spore
species, then, you know, it's it's easy
to powder them and and we can track that
all the way through from, you know,
right down from the spore through all
the different agar plates and and and
that kind of piece to the patient and
what they consumed and how much and even
what their outcomes are. But if we have
several different um varieties going
into a powder, so maybe we have a golden
teacher in one and an ape in another,
then that becomes a lot harder to know
where what was the base spore that that
came from when we just throw them all
into one bag of powder.
That makes sense.
So maybe some parameters on if you're
working with a species then it has to be
just one um one type that gets powdered
uh that you're not you're not doing
multi multispore or that kind of thing.
>> Yeah, I agree with that.
>> Dave,
>> next that we have David. Yeah, your mic
is enabled.
Yeah, just to piggy back off of what
Greg was saying, um,
as far as like homogenity through a
sample or a cult of our specifically, it
also goes into if you're cult if the
cultivator is using a multis-pore or
using a tissue culture, it's a lot
easier to get consistent percentages
through a what you would call a flush,
which would be a a
uh mushrooms fruing is called the flush,
right? And so to get a consistent flush,
if you're using tissue culture, it's a
lot easier to get a consistent
percentage because you're basically
cloning an individual mushroom
uh rather than multis-pore like uh Greg
mentioned will give you results. Every
single mushroom in that batch, if we're
going to call it a batch per se, is
going to have a different percentage and
can grow. It's kind of like similar to a
cannabis plant. You know, you could take
a a a piece of the cannabis plant from
the top and a piece of cannabis plant
from the middle and a piece of cannabis
plant from the bottom and they're going
to have inconsistent percentage all
through that single plant. And as far as
I know for like cannabis, they're
testing, you know, one in 100 plants in
these really large grows. So, I think
the percentage
uh is kind of out the door. But if you
want to look to and model a good
homogenity test, uh the Scottsdale
Research Institute is the only institute
I know that's doing uh full fruit
bodies. And how they're using the
homogenity is very similar to like they
describe they they grow the entire batch
of a single cultivar, right? We don't
want to mix multiple cultivars in in the
batch and then grinding it up is the
most even way to distribute and get a a
clean consistent dose if we say dose. So
somebody mentioned putting them in
capsules. That's an excellent way to get
a accurate dose in a batch in that
sense. Um chocolates can be measured.
Somebody was asking about HLC in New
Mexico. I don't think there's any labs
doing HLC and that's basically potency
testing. Um, but you know, Colorado has
a lot of uh labs that are doing it.
Specifically, I would I would look to
try.
Um, there's a guy named Chris Pauly at
Tryptomics who's doing a lot of all of
this research. They're doing homogenity
testing through chocolates. They're
finding, you know, a lot of uh probably
I would say more than 50 to 60% of the
people that are putting out aftermarket
products are not actually using
psilocybin. They're using research
chemicals, 5H, you know, different uh
synthetic DMTs, different synthetic
things. So, um sticking to a few
cultivars, a few genuses. I mean, I'm
all in support of research for other
genuses, but as far as like variables go
in the process, uh, keeping it to simple
fruit bodies,
uh, in my personal opinion would be the
route to take. It's just a little bit
easier
um to keep uh
the procedures in order since this is
for medical. I think that would be the
best approach. But those are just my two
cents.
>> Thank you, Dave. Um, you know, I know
we're going to have to get some labs
stood up here in New Mexico because
we're not going to be able to transport
our product up to Colorado. Is that
correct, Dominic?
>> Uh, that is correct. Because it is
schedule one, we cannot cross borders
with products. Um because even though it
is legal in Colorado and would be legal
for medicinal purposes in New Mexico, uh
it still cannot cross that state border.
That's considered a federal border. And
so doing that is still illegal and
people would be subject to it. We have
had that experience. uh again with
regard to cannabis and uh I can tell you
right now we actually run um uh calls on
a fairly regular basis with individuals
uh who have crossed the border and
actually had their products either
confiscated or they themselves arrested
simply for crossing the border with
product. So it's not something that we
could be asking any of the permites to
do. None of the cultivators or anyone
else. We don't want to put them at that
risk. Um, one thing, um, just before is
I just want to make a time check, Chris.
We do have 12 minutes left in this time
frame. And, um, the other aspect of this
is, uh, we need to make sure that we're
staying on time. And so, uh, I think we
only have time for a few other people,
but I do want to make sure that we are
agreed. You had brought up earlier about
the, um, this group committee meeting
every two weeks. So, I just want to make
sure that with that in mind, we would be
looking um at that um the date for that
then would be Friday. Oh, I'm sorry. I
just my calendar just switched over to
February. My apologies. Uh we would be
looking at Friday the 23rd. Um and going
from 3 to 5:00 p.m. Is that correct?
I just want to make sure that we have
that and that people who are here on the
call know that. Um, so am I correct in
that, Chris?
>> Yeah, I would like to shift the next one
to Wednesday the 21st if we can. I'm
going to be in California running a
Spartan race that weekend, so I can't um
I can't do the 23rd, but Wednesday the
21st would be the my next meeting that I
would like to propose at from 3:00 to 5.
Uh, is that going to work for most
people?
>> Okay.
>> And then I want to give the the these
people a little bit more time to talk.
Um, but keep in mind the next meeting is
going to be focused on our cultivation
uh prior as a priority topic. Um, and
then once we kind of have a handle on
that, we'll step into testing and some
other other things. Um, but all of these
things that we're we're talking about
now, we'll continue in that meeting. Um,
but really kind of getting into like
what kind of substrates we should use,
what we shouldn't use, cleaning
products, all that type of stuff. I
really I'm going to need help on on
that. and and if there's information
that I could use to kind of get spun up
a little better, you know, like like I
said, I'm I'm working off the the uh
MGAP um protocols through the USDA right
now, but um I I can use more
information. If if there's something I
need to read, please reach out to me.
>> And just just as a reminder, if there's
documents or items or other information,
you can send it to the medical.silocybin
psilocybin dooh.nm.gov
email and we will get it forwarded. Uh
the main reason for doing this is to
ensure that items are running through in
such a way that we have transparency. Um
because that is one of the most
important aspects of this entire process
is to ensure that we have transparency
and uh that people don't think we're
trying to do things in the dark so to
speak. Um, and so we just want to make
sure I have put that information back up
um, on the slide and I will put it in
the uh, the meeting chat here in just a
moment.
>> Um, and then if we could go ahead with
our last three commenters and and each
of you please keep it brief maybe two
minutes piece.
>> Evans you may begin.
Yeah, just putting a pin for a
conversation about creating consistency.
Um, uh, the gentleman
that was Estabbon who was talking about
um, cloning and, uh, monocultures
essentially is what he was talking
about.
Um, [clears throat] if we had a license
for a geneticist that produces liquid
culture and distributes that liquid
culture, those could essentially like
that p like that entity could produce uh
consistently producing um inoculent and
if we
I don't know put put that into
conversation if if if that makes sense
to anybody if anyone wants to write it
down because I think that there's
potential to create more consistency
possibly through that process.
>> Thank you very much for that, Matthew. I
have Oh, your mic is enabled. Actually,
go ahead when you're ready.
>> Uh, yes, sir. So, my question is, what
if people still want to take it more
traditionally away? So, like not in a
capsule, but as a whole mushroom, will
there still be an avenue for people to
do that?
Uh, that's a good question and one I
think that we'll need to discuss
further.
>> Finally, there we have David.
You may begin now.
>> Oh, yeah. I just wanted to echo that
when I was mentioning the lab in Denver,
it's just a a good lab to model
standardization of HLC and those kind of
techniques and I totally understand that
we can't ship over state lines. Um, but
if a lab did happen to pop up in New
Mexico, I think that would be a
generally awesome resource to look to
for standardization of testing.
Fantastic. Those are all the comments.
Chris,
>> um
I just want to thank everyone for being
so
um
so involved and dedicated to this and
coming to these meetings. You all are
going to make program work and I'm so
grateful for all of you. Um, we kind of
ran out of time today and I know the the
Department of Health is going to be in
the middle of the legislative session,
but
maybe not next meeting, but the
following one I definitely want to be in
person. I think most of the people are
from the Albuquerque area, but I also
want to I want to get out and see some
people from other parts of the state um
because I I really uh value that
persontoperson interaction. So, I'll try
to do hybrid meetings uh upcoming, but
we'll we'll do the next one virtual as
well
as Estebon. We got a couple minutes
left. Go ahead.
>> Uh thank you. I just want to let anyone
in this group who is a cultivator know
that we are uh currently working on
accepting membership the New Mexico
Micology Guild. If you are interested in
joining, I'll drop an email in the chat
here. Um again, our express goals are
protecting the interests of instate
growers. um growers of all natures and
sizes here. Um as well as potentially
subsidizing things such as testing costs
and even equipment costs for local
growers.
>> Thank you very much for that.
>> All right, with that I think thank you
again everyone. Um, if nobody else has
anything, we'll uh conclude this meeting
for Go ahead, Dominic.
>> And I I just wanted to remind everyone
that we will have the recording and the
documents that we've reviewed will get
posted to the website. It can take 5 to
10 business days. We try to get it done
as soon as possible, but please uh bear
with us a little bit. And again, if you
have information that you were not able
to share here that you wanted to, you
can send it to our email, which we've
put in the chat several times. So,
please go right on ahead and do that. We
appreciate it. And uh on behalf of the
department, thank you everybody for your
work. The conversations are necessary
and needed. So, uh thank you all for
participating. And back to you, Chris,
for final any final comments.
>> Thank you all again. I think I've said
everything I need to. Appreciate you.
>> Thank you everybody. We are going to end
the meeting at this time. Chris, if you
stay for just a moment just to make sure
we have everybody uh closing off.